Finding Aid for Tuomy Family Papers, 1840-1966
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Tuomy Family papers 1840-1966, 1905-1945
Tuomy family.
1 oversize folders
3 linear feet
86138 Aa 2 UAm
Pioneer Ann Arbor, Michigan family, involved in farming, then real estate, developed the Tuomy Hills area of the city. Papers include personal and business correspondence of Cornelius and Kathryn Tuomy and of other family members; ledger books, 1868-1890, 1911-1938, and diaries, 1920-1921, 1925, 1926, 1936 concerning business and personal affairs; also papers of Kathryn G. Tuomy as president of the Michigan Federation of Business and Professional Women; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by the Tuomy estate (Donor No. 4597 ). Portions of the collection came from the Historical Society of Michigan, current residents of the Tuomy home.
The collection is open to research.
The Tuomy Family arrived in Scio Township in southeast Michigan from County Kerry, Ireland in 1838. Timothy Tuomy and his wife Johanna (Roache) Tuomy purchased one of the first farms in Washtenaw County, a tract of land west of Ann Arbor. Cornelius L. Tuomy was one of their nine children, born October 28, 1843 on the homestead in Scio. Cornelius L. bought an Ann Arbor township farm of two hundred and twenty acres in 1874 and the family home, referred to as Tuomy Place, is still standing at 2117 Washtenaw Avenue. Cornelius L. became one of the most successful and best known farmers in Washtenaw County.
In 1885, Cornelius L. Tuomy married Julia Ann Kearney, daughter of Thomas and Catherine (Duffy) Kearney of Northfield Township. Julia Ann had three siblings: brothers Thomas D. and John, and sisters Mary and Kate. Julia was the only one who married. Thomas D. Kearney was prosecuting attorney of Washtenaw County and the Ann Arbor city attorney. Cornelius L. and Julia A. Tuomy had three children: Cornelius William, born September 27, 1886; Kathyrn Genevieve, born September 13, 1888; and Thomas Kearney, born September 21, 1890. Cornelius L. Tuomy died in 1912 and Julia Ann Tuomy died at age 82 in 1938. Cornelius L. and Julia A. Tuomy had three children: Cornelius William, born September 27, 1886; Kathyrn Genevieve, born September 13, 1888; and Thomas Kearney, born September 21, 1890. Cornelius L. Tuomy died in 1912 and Julia Ann Tuomy died at age 82 in 1938.
Cornelius W. (Bill) Tuomy was a lifelong resident of Tuomy Place, except for his time in the Army. He was a World War I veteran and served several terms as county drain commissioner between 1930 and 1944. For more than fifty years, Bill Tuomy was in the real estate and insurance business in Ann Arbor with his sister Kathryn, in the firm known as Tuomy and Tuomy. The family was responsible for the development of the Tuomy Hills area of Ann Arbor (the former Tuomy farm), and established the Tuomy Hills Gas Station at Washtenaw and Stadium Roads. There is a road named for the family that borders the west boundary of Tuomy Place. Cornelius W. Tuomy died in March 1966 at age 69.
Kathryn G. Tuomy graduated from the University of Michigan in 1912. Except for two years that she taught business classes in Kenosha, Wisconsin (1914-1915), she spent all of her life in Ann Arbor at Tuomy Place. For some years she was in sole charge of the family real estate business, the oldest real estate office in Ann Arbor. Kathryn Tuomy was also a president of the Michigan Federation of Business and Professional Women and active in associated women's clubs. Her other brother, Thomas Kearney Tuomy, was a local athletic star but contracted pneumonia at age 28 and died in 1918. Kathryn G. Tuomy died at age 76 in 1965.
Cornelius W. Tuomy was the last surviving member of the Tuomy family of Ann Arbor. He bequeathed a large portion of his family estate to the St. Francis of Assisi Catholic Parish in the city. The family residence, Tuomy Place, is now the home of the Historical Society of Michigan.
The Tuomy Family papers document the daily life of three generations of a pioneer Ann Arbor area family. The three linear feet of papers span the years 1840-1966 with the bulk of the material falling within the decades bound by 1905-1945. The papers have been divided into four series, a small set of documents with biographical information, a larger set of personal and business correspondence, and family material arranged as a set of topical files. There is also a box of unidentified family portraits
A strength of the Tuomy Family papers is the documentation of daily life for a prominent Ann Arbor family from 1900 until the 1960's. Kathryn G. Tuomy's materials provide good exposure to the life of an Ann Arbor woman who has a university education and a family business to maintain. The papers are weaker in their coverage of the Tuomy and Tuomy real estate business. There is only marginal documentation regarding Cornelius W. (Bill) Tuomy's time in political office as drain commissioner. The photographs are not strongly backed up by the written documentation regarding the Tuomy and Tuomy real estate office and properties.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Business records.; Catholic Church.; Irish Americans--Michigan.; Michigan Federation of Business and Professional Women.; Prohibition--Michigan.; Protestant Churches.; Real estate business--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Tuomy, Cornelius L., 1843-1912.; Tuomy, Julia Ann, 1855-1938.; Tuomy, Thomas Kearney.; Tuomy family.; University of Michigan--Football.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Belle Isle Bridge (Detroit, Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); Detroit Opera House (Detroit, Mich.); Detroit River (Mich. and Ont.); Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928.; Huron Towers (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Lamp Post Motel (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Offices--Michigan--Lansing--1915.; St. Patrick's Church (Northfield, Mich.); Streets--Michigan--Detroit.; Tuomy, Cornelius William, 1886-1966.; Tuomy, Kathryn Genevieve, 1888-1965.; Tuomy, Thomas Kearney.; Tuomy Hills Gas Station (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Tuomy House (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Contributors:
Tuomy, Cornelius William, 1886-1966.; Tuomy, Kathryn Genevieve, 1888-1965.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Diaries.; Photographs.
- Biographical Information
  The Biographical Information series provides a good overview of the three generations of the Tuomy family covered by these papers. The obituaries and the biographical sketches of Cornilius L. and Kathryn G. Tuomy provide helpful orientation to the family relationships and names. The Final Will and Testament, generated by Cornelius W. (Bill) Tuomy and executed in 1966, gives explanations for how the family home, estate and property have been distributed.
  - Family Obituaries 1912-1966 (Box 1)
  - Tuomy, Cornelius L.-Biographical Sketches (Box 1)
  - Tuomy, Kathryn G.-Biographical Sketches (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Personal and Business
  The Correspondence series is a rich source of family information and includes some business interactions. A majority of the material in the Correspondence series is written as person letters between the three Tuomy siblings or addressed to their mother, Julia. A large amount of writing occurred at the time that Cornelius W. (Bill) Tuomy was in the Army in 1918. Kathryn G. Tuomy also exchanged a large amount of correspondence in 1929-1931, when she was very active in the local and national Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs. Family friends, including Frank McIntyre (especially 1940-1941), a newspaper man and entertainer, and in-laws on the Kearney side are also contributors to the conversations carried on in the Correspondence series. Interspersed with the personal correspondence are some letters (especially 1932-1933) on rental properties and real estate concerns of the Tuomy and Tuomy real estate office.
  - 1840 (Box 1)
  - 1874 1876 (Box 1)
  - 1885 (Box 1)
  - 1900-1909 (Box 1)
  - 1910-1913 (Box 1)
  - 1914-1915 (Box 1)
  - 1916-1917 (Box 1)
  - 1918, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1919-1920 (Box 1)
  - 1921-1923 (Box 1)
  - 1924-1925 (Box 1)
  - 1926-1928 (Box 1)
  - 1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1931 (Box 1)
  - 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - 1934-1935 (Box 1)
  - 1936-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1965 (Box 1)
  - Undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Topical File
  The Topical File series is a mixture of various interests and activities of Tuomy family members and extends to material relating to the Kearney family (the relatives of Julia A. Tuomy). The Kearney family folders give brief views of the daily lives of two of Julia A. Tuomy's sisters. Julia's father, Thomas D. Kearney, had records that relate to his land acquisitions and business transactions in and around Ann Arbor.
  The ledger records from 1868 to 1890 show a detailed record of farm and business interactions as Cornelius L. Tuomy ran a successful farm and bought land. Julia A. Tuomy, his wife, continued the ledger records in the form of account books, from 1911-1938. Taken together, these ledgers provide a rich description of the daily transactions involved in a growing family estate and successful business ventures in Ann Arbor during this period.
  The Topical File folders for Kathryn G. Tuomy include specific information on the women's clubs in which she was active (including photographs) and contain some motivational speeches. Thomas Kearney Tuomy folders contain a small amount of information on his activities before his death from influenza and pneumonia at age 28. Cornelius W. (Bill) Tuomy's Topical File folders include his army enlistment exams, some background information regarding his political interests, and his American Legion activities.
  - Kearney Family Correspondence 1902-1936, undated (Box 1)
  - Kearney, Julia
    - Scrapbook 1890s-1950s (Box 1)
  - Kearney, Kathryn V.
    - Scrapbook with Obituaries and Poems 1886-1926 (Box 1)
  - Kearney, Mary E.
    - Diary, 1920-1921 (Box 1)
  - Kearney, Thomas D.
    - Speech 1917 (Box 1)
    - Diaries, 1925, 1926 (Box 1)
    - Land Estimate Sketch Book, ca. 1913-1915 and Ann Arbor Residence Drawing (Box 1)
  - Tuomy Family
    - Family Photographs (Box 2)
    - Family Residence 2117 Washtenaw Ave. (Box 2)
      (includes photographs)
    - History of the Family Name (Box 2)
    - Nixon and Kennedy Visits to Ann Arbor 1961 (Box 2)
  - Tuomy, Cornelius L.
    - Ledger 1868-1890 (Box 2)
    - Land and Ann Arbor Township Farm Notes 1886-1898 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Township Farm Purchase Records, ca. 1874-1888 (Box 2)
  - Tuomy, Cornelius W.
    - Army Enlistment 1917 (Box 2)
    - American Legion Scrapbook 1927-1928 (Box 2)
    - Republican National Convention June 14, 1932 (Box 2)
    - Candidate for Drain Commissioner, Ann Arbor 1938 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan Band 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    - Last Will and Testament 1965 (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Tuomy, Julia A.
    - Account Book 1911-1914 (Box 2)
    - Account Book 1914-1920 (Box 2)
    - Account Book 1920-1927 (Box 2)
    - Account Book 1927-1938 (Box 2)
    - Diary, 1936 (Box 2)
    - Property on Washtenaw Avenue undated (Box 2)
  - Tuomy, Kathryn G.
    - Memorabilia 1908-1912 (Box 2)
    - Essays on the Business World, ca. 1914 (Box 2)
    - List of University of Michigan Class of 1912 ca. 1929 (Box 2)
    - Business and Professional Women's Club of Ann Arbor 1925, 1947-1949 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Federation of Business and Professional Women 1929-1930 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Federation of Business and Professional Women, ca. 1930 (Box 2)
    - National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Inc. 1929, 1931 (Box 2)
    - International Federation of Business and Professional Women 1934-1936 (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Tuomy, Thomas Kearney
    - Football (Detroit University School) and School Papers 1909-circa 1912 (Box 2)
      (includes photograph)
    - Poem to Thomas Kearney Tuomy 1918 (Box 2)
  - Tuomy and Tuomy Properties
    - Diary for Phone Messages 1940 (Box 2)
    - Business Buildings, ca. 1940-1960 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Buildings, ca. 1950s (Box 2)
      (includes slides)
    - Construction, ca. 1955-1964 (Box 2)
    - Notebook, ca. 1960s (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Homes 1960-1964, undated (Box 2)
    - Tuomy Hills Gas Station, ca. 1930 and ca. 1960-1965 (Box 2)
    - Tuomy and Tuomy Real Estate Office, ca. 1961-1963 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The collection also contains photographs scattered throughout the Topical Files and in the Photographs series. The photographs show the Tuomy family, their home on Washtenaw Avenue, their real estate office and gas station. In addition, there are numerous images of Kearney and Tuomy family members, unfortunately mainly unidentified.
  - Collected photographs of Detroit, with views of Detroit Opera House fire, Governor Pingree on military inspection, Belle Isle Bridge, etc. 1897 (Box 2)
  - Family portraits and albums (Box 3)
  - Photograph of Woodbridge Ferris in his office 1915 photograph of St. Patrick Church; and photograph of U-M student group in costume (Folder UAm)